Call me Jonah. My parents did or nearly did. They called me John.
Jonah, John, if I'd been a Sam, I would have been a Jonah still.
Not because I've been unlucky for others, but because somebody or something has compelled me to be certain places at certain times without fail.
Conveyances and motives both conventional and bizarre have been provided.
And according to plan, at each appointed second, at each appointed place, this Jonah was there.
Listen, when I was a younger man, two wives ago, 250,000 cigarettes ago, 3,000 quarts of booze ago,
When I was a much younger man, I began to collect material for a book to be called The Day the World Ended.
The book was to be factual.
The book was to be an account of what important Americans had done on the day when the first atomic bomb was dropped on Hiroshima, Japan.
It was to be a Christian book. I was a Christian then.
I am a Bacconinist now.
I would have been a Bacconinist then, if there had been anyone to teach me the bittersweet lies of Bacconin.
But Bacconinism was unknown beyond the gravel beaches and coral knives that ring this little island in the Caribbean Sea, the Republic of San Lorenzo.
We Bacconinists believe that humanity is organized into teams, teams that do God's will without ever discovering what they are doing.
Such a team is called a caress by Bacconin, and the instrument, the can-can, that brought me into my own particular caress was the book I never finished.
The book to be called The Day the World Ended.
If you find your life tangled up with somebody else's life for no very logical reasons, writes Bacconin, that person may be a member of your caress.
At another point in the books of Bacconin, he tells us,
Man created the checkerboard. God created the caress.
By that he means that a caress ignores national, institutional, occupational, familial, and class boundaries.
It is as free form as an amoeba.
In his 53rd Calypso, Bacconin invites us to sing along with him.
Oh, a sleeping drunkard up in Central Park, and a lion hunter in the jungle dark,
And a Chinese dentist and a British queen, all fit together in the same machine.
Nice, nice, very nice, nice, nice, very nice, nice, nice, very nice.
Many different people in the same device.
About my caress, then, it surely includes the three children of Dr. Felix Hunniker,
One of the so-called fathers of the first atomic bomb.
Dr. Hunniker himself was no doubt a member of my caress.
Though he was dead before my sanukas, the tendrils of my life, began to tangle with those of his children.
The first of his heirs to be touched by my sanukas was Newton Hunniker, the youngest of his three children.
The younger of his two sons.
I wrote this letter to Newt.
Dear Mr. Hunniker,
I am gathering material for a book relating to the first atomic bomb.
Since your late father is generally recognized as having been one of the chief...
That you learn how to read.