teams that do God's will without ever discovering what they are doing.
that person may be a member of your korass.
very nice so many different people in the same device.
by my sonukas was Newton-Hunaker, the youngest of his three children, the younger of his two sons.
He stayed home whenever he wanted to. was where he died. He died on a Christmas Eve. You probably know that too.
It was to be a Christian book. I was a Christian then. I am a Baconanist now.
I would have been a your illustrious family as I should and so don't know whether you have brothers or sisters. I was only six years old when they dropped the atomic bomb on Hiroshima, so anything I remember about that day This Jonah was there. Father, as you probably know, spent practically his whole professional life working for the Listen, when I was a younger man, two wives ago, Call me Jonah.
About my karass then, it surely includes the three children of Dr.
Oh, a sleeping drunkard up in Central Park, and a lion hunter in the jungle dark, and a At another point in the books of Bekonen he tells us, Such a team is called a karass by Bekonen and the instrument, My parents did or nearly did. They called me John. If you do have brothers and sisters I would like very much to have their addresses so that I can Anyway, I was playing on the carpet outside his study on the day of the bomb. 250,000 cigarettes ago, 3,000 quarts of booze ago, I wrote this letter to Newt. other people have helped me to remember. research laboratory of the General Forge and Foundry Company in Ilium. man created the checkerboard, Baconanist then, if there had been anyone to teach me the bittersweet lies of Jonah, John, if I'd been a Sam, I would have been a Jonah still. Dear Mr. Hunneker, I'm gathering material for a book relating to the first atomic bomb.
Felix Hunaker the can-can that brought me into my own particular karass was the book I never finished. God created the karass. send similar requests to them. I realize that you were a very young man when the bomb I remember I was playing in the living room carpet outside my father's study in Ilium, New York.
when I was a much younger man, My sister Angela tells me, I used to play with little toy trucks for hours making motor sounds, Chinese dentist and a British queen, all fit together in the same machine.
Nice, nice, very nice, nice, nice, nice, very nice, nice, nice, very nice, nice, very nice, nice, very nice, nice, very nice, nice, nice, very nice, nice, nice, nice, nice, nice, very nice, nice, nice, By that he means that a korass ignores national, When the Manhattan Project came along, the bomb project, father wouldn't leave Ilium to work on it. He said he wouldn't work on it at all unless they let him work where he wanted to work. A lot of the time that meant at home.
The only place he liked to go outside of Baconan. But Baconanism was unknown beyond the gravel beaches and coral knives that ring this little island in the Caribbean Sea, the Republic of San Lorenzo. Not because I've been unlucky for others, but because somebody or something has compelled me to be certain places at certain times I began to collect material for a book to be called one of the so-called fathers of the first atomic bomb. Dr. Hunaker himself was no doubt a member of my Since your late father is generally recognized as having been one of the chief creators of the bomb, The book to be called The Day the World Ended. The the world ended. institutional, occupational, familial, and class boundaries. going Burton, Burton, Burton, Burton all the time. So I guess I was going Burton, Burton, Burton, The book was to be factual. without fail. Conveyances and motives both conventional and bizarre have been provided. I would very much appreciate any anecdotes you might care to give me of life in your father's house on the dropped. It is as free form as an amoeba. karass, though he was dead before my sinukas, the tendrils of my life, began to tangle with those of his children. The book was to be an account of what important Americans had done on the day on the day of the bomb. And father was in his study playing with the loop of string. In his 53rd kalipso, when the first atomic bomb was dropped on Hiroshima, Japan. And according to plan, at each appointed second, at each appointed place, nice, I'm sick of people misunderstanding what a scientist is, what a scientist does, he said.
companies that actually hires men to do pure research.
The general as their spokesman felt that one of the aspects of progress should be the Marines no longer had to fight in mud is this desk. Dr. Breed banged he speckled old fist on the desk.
The desk was a is only one of several types of ice. determined how each subsequent layer would stack and lock. Nothing generous about it, he said. cynical. We climbed the four granite steps before the research laboratory. Likes and dislikes have nothing to do with it, says Bekonin. His head is full of projects of his own and that's the way we want it. That old man asked me to think of United States Marines in a God-forsaken swamp. There are several ways, Dr Breed said to me, in which certain liquids can crystallize, can New knowledge is the most valuable commodity on earth.
What did the general have in mind? kidney-shaped, seagreen steel affair.
Suppose water always froze as ice one on earth because it had never had a seed to teach it how to form When most other companies brag about their research, they're talking about industrial It's an easy warning to forget. The bottom layer is the seat of how every cannonball or every orange that comes after is going to behave, Did anybody ever try to suggest projects to Dr. Hunaker, I said. I'll do my best to clear up the misunderstanding, I said. The more truth we have to work with, the richer we become. Their trucks and tanks and howitzers are wallowing, he complains, sinking and stinking me asthma and ooze.
Certainly he said, admirals and generals in particular. The absence of mud said Dr.
One marine could carry more than enough of the freeze, several ways in which their atoms can stack and lock in an orderly rigid way. The building itself was of unadorned brick and rose six stories. We passed Dr Breed made an appointment with me for early the next morning. hacked technicians who wear white coats work out of cookbooks and dream up an improved In this country he said most people don't even understand what pure research is. ice two, ice three, ice four. Had I been a baconanist then, that statement would have made me how.
Breed no more mud even to an infinite number of cannonballs and oranges. He would pick me up at my hotel. between two heavily armed guards at the entrance. I smiled at one of the guards.
Do you mean, I said to Dr. Breed that nobody in this laboratory has ever told what to work on?
thus simplifying my entry into the heavily guarded research laboratory.
Now suppose, Chortle Dr Breed, enjoying himself, that there were many possible ways in which water could crystallize, could freeze.
But here I asked him, here, and shockingly few other places in this country, men are paid to increased knowledge, to work to no end but that.
He did not stuff to free an armored division bogged down in the everglades. According to Felix, one marine windshield wiper or next year's Oldsmobile. He raised a finger and winked at me.
smile back. There was nothing funny about national security, nothing at all. When we got to Dr Breed's inner office started to ask Dr Breed questions about the day of the bomb.
It isn't looking for a better cigarette filter or a softer face tissue or a longer lasting house pain. God help us.
I remember shortly before Felix died, there was a marine general who was hounding him to do something about mud.
And suppose, and he wrapped on his desk with his old hand again, that there were one form, which we will call ice nine, They looked upon him as a sort of magician who could make America invincible with a wave of his wand. And what did Dr. Hunaker say in his playful way and all his ways were playful On his way to work, he said, I'd appreciate it if you tell me what it is. That old man with spotted hands invited me to think of the several ways in which cannonballs might be But suppose young man that one Marine had with him a tiny capsule containing a seed of Ice Nine, a new way for the atoms of water to stack and lock to freeze.
stacked on a courthouse lawn, or the several ways in which oranges might be packed into a crate.
Nobody even suggests what they work on? the crystal as hard as this desk with a melting point of, oh, let us say, 100 degrees Fahrenheit, or better still, a melting point of 130 degrees.
Breed was a pink old man, very prosperous, beautifully dressed.
Oh, people suggest things all the time. Mud, I said. The Marines after almost 200 years of wallowing in mud.
Suppose that the sort of ice we skate upon and put into high balls, If that threw that seed into the nearest puddle, the puddle, the puddle freeze, His manner was civilized, optimistic, capable, serene.
Everybody talks about research and practically nobody in the country is doing it.
And he helped me to see that the pattern of the bottom layers of the cannon balls, I said to him that's very generous of General Forge and Foundry it isn't in the nature of a pure research man to pay attention to attention to attention to attention to attention to suggest.
the cannonballs of orange.
in order to give you some insight into the extraordinary novelty of the ways in which Felix was isn't, I said. I just told you there wasn't, cried Dr Breed hotly.
Felix died shortly after that, and if you've the swamp froze as Ice Nine, I said. What about the rivers and the lakes?
The streams if I'd known you were a member of the Yellow Press, I wouldn't have wasted a minute with you.
before going to his just reward. He did it without anyone's realizing what he was doing.
Angela had been 34, Freedom-loving beautiful nation makes itself extremely attractive to American investors and tourists alike.
them, this unattractive child was identified as Major General Franklin Hunaker, General Franklin Hunaker.
In the essay, Frank told of being all alone on a nearly swamped And all the muck around the puddle, he said, it would freeze. She was the adopted daughter of the dictator of the island. was in a special supplement to the New York Sunday Times. The supplement was a paid Frank had been 24, little Newt had been 18.
I opened a supplement hoping for more pictures of this sublime, And all the puddles in the frozen muck, he said. likely to approach an old problem. fed. They'd freeze, but there is no such thing as Ice Nine.
And the oceans, the frozen rivers In the rain, I said, when it fell it would freeze into hard little hobnails of Ice Nine, The old man had died on Christmas Eve 68 foot criss-craft on the Caribbean. He didn't explain what he was doing on it or how he Minister of Science and Progress in the Republic of San Lorenzo. He did it without leaving records of what he had done. He had made a chip of Ice Nine. ad for a banana republic. On its cover was a profile of the most heartbreakingly beautiful girl They would freeze. What I've just told you is what he told a Marine general who was hounding him about mud. I was in no hurry to read the contents. Madonna.
been listening to what I've been trying to tell you about pure research men, you wouldn't having told only his children about Ice Nine. And the pools and streams in the frozen muck, he said. I found instead a portrait of the island's dictator, Miguel Papa Munzano, He was 26 years old. The girl on the cover was enough for me, more than enough since I had fallen in love with her on sight. fed? They'd freeze, of course, he snapped. I suppose you're going to rush to market with a sensational story about Ice Nine now. I tell you, again, it does not exist. And the springs feeding the frozen lakes and streams, I said, and all the water underground feeding the springs? and that would be the end of the world and the end of the interview too. Goodbye! It was blue-white. It had a melting point of 114.4 degrees Fahrenheit. Felix Hunaker had put the happened to be alone. He did indicate, though, that his point of departure had been Cuba. They would freeze. Felix ate alone here in the cafeteria every day. His children had divided the Ice Nine among themselves. I wondered how Franklin Hunaker, who had never even finished high school, had got himself such a fancy job. You bet they would, he cried. a gorilla in his late 70s. It was a rule that no one was to sit with him to interrupt his chain of thought, but the Marine general barged in, pulled up a chair and started talking about mud. And the United States Marines would rise from the swamp and march on. She was very young and very grave too, and luminously compassionate and wise. Next to Papa's portrait was a picture of a narrow-shouldered fox-faced, immature young man. Dr Breed was mistaken about at least one thing. There was such a thing as Ice Nine, and Ice Nine was on Earth. Ice Nine was the last gift,! The luxurious pleasure craft was going down in my meaningless life with it, said the essay, all I'd eaten for four days was two biscuits and a seagull. The dorsal fins of mane I found a partial answer in a Florida essay titled, What San Lorenzo has meant to one American. She was as brown as chocolate, her hair was like golden flax. Her name was Mona Ammons, monzano, the cover said. He wore a snow-white military blouse with some sort of jeweled sunburst hanging on it. I've told you was Felix's off-hand reply. It was almost certainly ghost written. Felix Hunanker, Fund. He offered Johnson $500 for transportation to Miami. The two set sail from Miami.
You'll never believe it, she said, but I just found two more Hoosiers on this When Lionel Boyd Johnson and Corporal Earl McCabe were washed up naked onto the shore of Tobago, alone in the lady slipper again.
But a said Crosby, but I don't say it's bad either. I sometimes wonder if something like that wouldn't clear thing I asked her, the hook down in the chamber of horrors in the basement. They had a wax person hanging When I again took my seat, Minton handed me the manuscript he and his wife had been reading. Conan on the page before me. Those words leaped out from the page and into my mind and they were Boyd Johnson was intellectually ambitious enough in 1911 to sail alone from Tobago to London in a was hospitalized for two years and then discharged. And he set sail for home for Indeed, though not grotesque, he was as nicely scaled as Gulliver among the Brobdignagians, and a shrewdly watchful too. humor and considerable information about the outside world. Aixelow Crosby's wife, Hazel. She was standing in the aisle next to me. Monzano, the woman I loved. Bek You're... Bek. and...!!! From the Calypso's again. up juvenile delinquency. Maybe the hook's a little extreme for a democracy. Public hangings more like it.
In 1922 he sought shelter from a up from a hook in Madame Two Soads. It looked so real I wanted to throw up. As it happened, as it was welcomed there. The words were paraphrases of the suggestion by Jesus, render therefore sloop named the Lady Slipper. His purpose was to gain a higher education.
He enrolled in the The name of the book was San Lorenzo, the land, the history, the people. gale hounded the schooner onto the rocks of San Lorenzo. The boat went down. Johnson I asked if they were bound for a family reunion with Frank and San Lorenzo, said Angela, Oh, a very sorry people, yes, did I find here? San Lorenzo, I read, they were greeted by persons far worse off than they. airplane. I'll be damned, I said. Her name is Connors and his name is Hunnaker. So I went String up a few teenage car thieves on lamp posts in front of their houses, was signed around their neck saying, under Caesar the things which are Caesars. Conan's paraphrase was this, pay no attention to Caesar. hurricane in Port of France, Haiti, which country was then occupied by United States Marines. Johnson was approached there by a brilliant The author was Philip Castle, the son of Julian Castle, the son of the great altruist I was on my way to see. and McCabe, absolutely naked, managed to swim ashore. How he came by the name of Bakonin was pronunciation given the name Johnson in the island's English dialect. Oh, they had no music and they had no beer. supposed to happen, my seatmates were Horik Minton, the new American Ambassador to the Republic of San Lorenzo and his wife Claire. They were reading a fat typewritten manuscript that was spread across the chair arm between them. were going to the engagement party. Oh, I said, who's the lucky girl? I'll show you, said Angela. And then she showed me a picture of the girl Frank was going to marry. She might with equal effect of struck me in the groin. The The people of San Lorenzo had nothing but diseases, which they were at a loss to treat or even name. Bekonan Mama, here's your boy. Do that a few times and I think ignition locks would go the way of the rumble seat and running boards. learned talk to Angela Hunneker, Conners, and little Newton-Hunaker, members of my caras. Angela was a horse-faced platinum blonde I had noticed earlier. from! Bekonan, I learned from was born in 1891. He was And everywhere where they tried to perch belonged to Castle Sugar, Incorporated, or the Catholic Church. Caesar doesn't have the slightest idea what's really going on. I let the book fall open where it would. a Negro, born in a Piscopalian and a British subject on the island of Tobago.! By contrast, Johnson and McCabe had the glittering treasures of literacy, ambition, curiosity, As it happened, it fell open to the chapter about the island's outlawed Holy Man, Bakunen. mercy in the jungle.
a free hospital for his people. So Bakonin made it his business to provide the people with better and better lies.
is a form of treason.
for six of those years. He's doing penance at the house of hope and mercy, is he now?
let the chips fall where they may. things go. That's right. What would you say to $100,000 a year?
About this Franklin Huncker, the pinch-faced child spoke with the timber and conviction of a kazoo.
Baconinist, the hook notwithstanding.
as a living legend of the cruel tyrant in the city and the gentle holy man in the jungle grew, I said. It's what we've baconon us say, he said, when we feel that a lot of mysterious things are going on.
Maybe you'd better come to the point, I said.
When Baconin and McCabe took over this miserable country Tell me, doctor, I said to Julian Castle, how is Papa Munsono? How can you possibly know what kind of a person I am? Bekonen suggested the hook too as the proper punishment for Bekonenus, the doctor said.
Papa doesn't like the way we treat the whole patient, said Castle, Good God, I cried. What would I have to do for that?
We've just met, I said. How did he come to be an outlaw? I asked. There's no sense in beating around the bush, he said.
Yes, said Castle, and making great strides too, saving lives right and left.
so too did the happiness of the people grow. particular the whole patient when he's dying. You? I was amazed. A bacononist too? He gazed at me levely. You too. You'll find out.
How would I know, he said? I had heard it said in the army that such and such a man spoke like a man with a paper rectum.
Your clothes, he said, the way you talk.
years ago, said Julian Castle, they threw out the priests, and then Baconin, cynically It was something he'd seen in the chamber of horrors at Madame Touss. It was his own idea.
He asked McCabe to outlaw him in his religion too, in order to give the religious life of the people Practically nothing, he said, and you'd drink out of gold goblets every night and eat off gold plates and have I'm a pretty good judge of character if I do say so myself. He put his hand on my shoulders again. I thought you'd probably been treating him, I said. At the house of hope and mercy in the jungle, Do people still die on the hook? I asked. I like the cut of your jib. we administer the last rights of the Bekoninous church to those who want them. Good for him, I said.
The last thing he said to me, which was about three years ago, was it the only thing that kept me off the hook was my American citizenship.!
to do it enthusiastically, but I was still at sea. I have no doubt of it, I said. He executes one every two years just to keep the pot boiling, so to speak, said the doctor.
Castle quoted this poem, which does not appear in the books of Bakonin.
We've both got things that he said. Am I to understand, I said, that you are offering me some kind of job here in San Lorenzo?
Yes, if he keeps going at his present rate, working night and day, the number of people he die in the year He winked ghouishly. That was for zest too. We don't speak, said Castle. And I'd like the cut of your jib. It's inevitably fatal. Such a man was general Huncker. and playfully, invented a new religion.
And I want to talk cold turkey to you, man to He laughed. You haven't caught on yet?
Me? President, I gasped. Who else is there, he said. This is nuts, I said, said.
And he took me down to what he called his den, den, in order that we might, spade, He sighed, looking up at the evening sky, busy, busy So I said goodbye to government and I gave my reason, that a really good religion.
I know I said, well, when it became real instrument of hope, So you said, Frank was frantic for me to complete his thought, a palace all your own? What's the job, I said? The President of the Republic of San Lorenzo. Thank you, I said. He smiled. I mean I said, does Papa really have people executed that way? Now, hoping to be hearty and persuasive, he said tenny things to me, things like, I like the cut of your jib. more zest, more tang. He wrote a little poem about it incidentally. He doesn't speak to me, that is. I think you and I could really hit it off. I gather I said that there are still several Bekoninous on the island, despite the laws, despite the hook. McCabe and Bekonen did not succeed in raising what is generally thought of is the standard of living, said Castle. The truth was that life was as short and brutish and mean as ever, but people didn't have to pay as much attention to the awful truth.!
before and so had never believed that such support was available.
Now I found that I had to believe of his head and soles of his feet, with the rest of his body forming a bridge whose futile it is to write or read histories.
Without accurate records of the past, how can men and When I turned to look at him he told me his hands poised over the water he was dead as hard as a statue Von Kennezfeld touched the tip of his tongue to the blue-white mystery. Veteran Grand, I knew Ice Nine for what it was. I had seen it often in my dreams. to the music of his fingers. little Zinca that wincem troll of Ukrainian ballet. I was without common. But the bodies still places to live for all, and good schools and good health and good times for all, and work for all who I asked him. The Hunakers were with me. We had locked Papa's door and had spread the word among the household staff that Papa was feeling much better. I remembered the cylinder Papa had hung around his neck and I made an obvious We'll sweep up the big pieces on the floor, Let's clean up the mess first, said Frank, and then we can talk. Frost bloomed on his lips. melt them in a bucket on a hot plate, he said. guesses to its contents. arched thrust toward the ceiling.
He was shaped like an iron, and Papa's lips and nostrils and women be expected to avoid making serious mistakes in the future? He asks ironically. wanted it. in it and I did. I pondered asking Bakonin to join my government, thus bringing about a He froze solid, totted, and crashed. Sionide? I gathered that the Republic of San Lorenzo and the three Hunnicars weren't the only ones who had Then we'll go over every square inch of the floor with a blowtorch in case there are any Things Bekonan and I were in no position to provide. I could see Frank dissociating himself from the causes of the mess, as you see him I brushed my fingers over his lips Sionide? had to be carried to the funeral pyre.
microscopic crystals. identifying himself with growing pride in energy, with the purifiers, the world savers, the cleaners up.
I was met by Dr. Schlichte, Kurnick's vault, who was bounding from Papa's bedroom.
Ice Nine.
Apparently the United States of America and the Union of Soviet Socialist Chunks skittered all over the floor. So again, Papa Manzano was the first man in history to die of Ice Nine.
They looked so peculiar he put his hands into the water what chemicals could possibly What we'll do with the bodies and the bed sort of millennium for my people.
We decided that this should be done with pomp, that Soldiers were now building a funeral pyre out by the hook. They did not know what the pyre was for. Sionite turns a man to cement in a second. The blue-white hemisphere shattered. eyeballs were glazed with a blue-white frost. Such a syndrome is no novelty now, God knows. But it certainly was then.
I've never seen such a rigid corpse before. He had a wild look. He took me by the arms and he cried, what is it? What was it, he had hanging around his neck? I beg your pardon, I said, he took it.
Soldiers and-Mozano's bedroom.
And I thought of ordering that awful hook outside the palace Sement? I went through the door and bawled for help. Moreable? the bed out and thrown in? There were many, many secrets that day. Busy, busy, busy, suppose that the ceremonies might as well begin. There was a hum in the air, the six planes of the San Lorenzo the Air Force were coming.
Republics had it too. The United States had obtained it through Angela's husband, whose plant in Indianapolis was understandably surrounded by electrified fences and homicidal German Shepherds.
Brooms, dust pants, blowtarts, hot plate, buckets, he commanded, snapping fingers. You propose applying a blowtor the bodies, I asked him?
Frank was so charged with technical thinking now that he, that he was, that he was practically A funeral pyre, he cried, to be taken down at once amidst great rejoicing. But then I understood that a millennium would have to offer something more than a holy man in a position of power. really pleased with himself. The question trailed off von kernig's well raised his hands and the water in the basin came with them.
It was no longer water but a hemisphere vice nine Come look. One vault hustled me into Papa's bedroom.!! I closed the door and I put my back to it.